Finding Aid for Charles L. Stevenson Papers, 1841-1846 and 1925-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles L. Stevenson papers 1841-1846 1925-1979
Stevenson, Charles L. (Charles Leslie), 1908-1979.
85433 Aa 2
Papers, 1925-1979, of Charles L. Stevenson, professor of philosophy at the University of Michigan, and his wife, Louise Destler Stevenson. Correspondence with philosophers George E. Moore and Ludwig Wittgenstein; Stevenson-Destler courtship letters; student letters from Yale in the 1920's; also manuscripts and lecture notes on philosophy; diaries of Louise Stevenson; draft of her novel; and sermon books 1841, 1845-1846 of his great grandfather, the Rev. Isaac D. Williamson, New York state clergyman.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Nora Stevenson (donor no. 6436 ) in 1980. Periodic additions have been received.
The collection is closed to research without the permission of Mrs. Nora L. Stevenson. The collection is open to the Stevenson family.
Charles Leslie Stevenson was born June 27, 1908 in Cincinnati, Ohio. He received in BA from Yale University, 1930 with a major in English literature and a minor in music; he next studied criticism and philosophy at Cambridge University 1930-1933, then returned to the United States for his Ph.D. from Harvard in 1935.
He was an instructor at Harvard, 1937-1939 and assistant professor at Yale, 1939-1946. In 1946, he came to the University of Michigan, first as assistant professor, 1946-1949, and from 1949 until his death in as full professor.
Professor Stevenson was the author of Ethics and Language (1944) and Facts and Values (1963)
In 1930, Stevenson married Louise Ellen Destler. She died in 1963. In 1966, he married Nora Carroll Cary.
The Charles L. Stevenson papers consist of his student notebooks from Yale, Cambridge and Harvard Universities; course materials and notes for his lectures in philosophy courses at the University of Michigan and professional correspondence, including letters with Ludwig Wittgenstein and George E. Moore; professional writings; and personal and family papers. The collection is divided into the following series: Personal/biographical; Correspondence; Education: Yale, Cambridge, Harvard; Course materials and lecture notes: Yale, University of Michigan; Writings and Research Notes; Miscellaneous; Louise Destler Stevenson Papers; and Other Family Members.
Subjects:
Clergy--New York (State); Philosophy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Yale University.; Stevenson, Charles L. (Charles Leslie), 1908-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Stevenson, Charles L. (Charles Leslie), 1908-; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Moore, G. E. (George Edward), 1873-1958.; Stevenson, Louise Destler.; Williamson, I. D. (Isaac Dowd), 1807-1876.; Wittgenstein, Ludwig, 1889-1951.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Personal/biographical
  - Clipping, citation, etc. (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Chronological 1926-1945, 1951, 1963, 1975, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Special Correspondence
    (see also scattered throughout chronological correspondence files)
    - Moore, George E. (Box 1)
    - Wittgenstein, Ludwig (Box 1)
  - With Louise Destler (later Mrs. Charles E. Stevenson) 1925-1930, undated, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - To and from Louise Stevenson 1957 (Box 2)
  - Letters of CLS with his mother 1926-1928, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters of CLS and Louise to Mrs. Lewis W. Destler 1930-1933, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (mainly from daughter Louise)
  - Personal correspondence, family and friends 1932-1934, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (include letters to their mothers)
  - Correspondence of Louise Destler Stevenson's family, various dates (Box 2)
- Education: Yale, Cambridge, Harvard
  - Student essays, Yale 1926-1930, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Accounts (Yale) 1929 (Box 2)
  - Notes taken on the lectures of Ludwig Wittgenstein (Cambridge) to students circa 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Notebook on lectures of Ludwig Wittgenstein (Cambridge) circa 1931-1933 (Box 2)
  - Course notes from G.E. Moore's lectures on Metaphysics, Cambridge University circa 1931-1933 (Box 2)
  - Study essays, probably Cambridge circa 1931 (Box 2)
  - Unfinished papers, Harvard circa 1934-1935 (Box 2)
    (Broad Epistemological Problems; A Priori Knowledge; Dispositions and Cause: Contextual Definitions; and Illustrations of Heterological Paradox)
  - Course notes and essays, Harvard: Definitions 1935 (Box 2)
  - Course notes and essays, Harvard: Propositions 1935 (Box 2)
  - Dissertation, Harvard, draft, "The Emotive Meaning of Ethical Terms" circa 1935 (Box 2)
- Course materials and lecture notes: Yale, University of Michigan
  - Systematic philosophy 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - Plato 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Social philosophy 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Philosophical aspects of psychology 1948 (Box 3)
  - Introduction to philosophy 1951-1978, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Theory of knowledge 1951, 1955-1956, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Relativism in ethics 1952 (Box 3)
  - Ethics 1954 (Box 3)
  - British Empiricism 1972 (Box 3)
  - Aesthetics lectures; Philosophy of the Arts, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Phil. 16: Ethics and Aesthetics (Box 3)
  - Course on Hume and others (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Writings and Research Notes
  - "Ethics and Language" manuscript undated (Box 3)
  - "The Ethical Views of John Dewey," manuscript undated (Box 4)
  - "Rhythm: in English Verse and in Music" manuscript and drafts undated, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Logic of if 1965 (Box 4)
  - Philosophy miscellaneous 1944-1996 (Box 4)
  - Ethical fallibility: Ethics and Science circa 1966, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - "Evaluation and Interpretation in Aesthetics" 1949 (Box 4)
  - "On 'What is a Poem'" 1956 (Box 4)
  - "English Verse and Musical Measures" (Box 4)
  - "On the Language of Fiction" (preliminary draft) 1979 (Box 4)
  - Dewey-Mill Ends-Means ? (rough notes) (Box 4)
  - Intrinsic value -- Mill (rough notes), 2 folders (Box 4)
  - The Place of Science in Ethics (rough notes) (Box 4)
  - Meaning of good; assumptions (rough notes) (Box 4)
  - Effusions (value) 1977-1978 (rough notes) (Box 4)
  - "If's and Horseshoes" (Box 4)
  - "The status of 'If' in Standard Modal Logic" (Box 4)
  - "Value-Judgments: Their Implicit Generality" 1977 (Box 4)
    (paper and correspondence relating to lecture given at University of Vermont)
  - "Some questions about emotive meaning" 1951 (Box 4)
  - "Poetry and the Aesthetic Attitude" 1957 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Braithwaithe's (perhaps R. B. Braithwaithe) class on Logic 1951-1952 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified notes circa 1979 (Box 4)
  - Outlines and quotes from books read (Box 4)
  - Baby Book 1908 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Louise Destler Stevenson Papers
  - Letters of Louise Destler 1925 written as history report on Revolutionary France (Box 5)
  - Diaries
    - 1935-1942 (Box 5)
    - 1942-1948 (Box 5)
    - 1948 (Box 5)
    - 1951-1962 (Box 5)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript, first draft of novel, "High Holborn" re-titled "Figures in a Landscape" circa 1940-1945, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Manuscript, draft of novel, "Figures in a Landscape" by Louise Destler Stevenson circa 1940-1945, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Outline for novel on Cincinnati by Louise Destler undated (Box 5)
  - Account book 1939-1940 (Box 5)
  - Account book 1940-1941 (Box 5)
  - Reading ledger, 3 volumes (Box 5)
- Other family members
  - Sermon books of Rev. Isaac Williamson, great-grandfather of Charles L. Stevenson
    (New York state clergyman)
    - 1841 (Box 5)
    - 1845-1846 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)